Boker Tov בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. All right, today's Daf דף Daf
is Peh Aleph. We start on Peh Amud Bet פה עמוד ב׳,
Peh Amud Bet, two dots, about ten lines from the bottom, Kol
HaOchlin כל האוכלין. Kol HaOchlin. We're doing the part about that all
the different types of foodstuff can combine for the minimum Kizayit כזית.
Kizayit. So Kol HaOchlin Mistarfin כל האוכלין מצטרפין. Kol HaOchlin Mistarfin. So
Amar Rav Papa אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa,
Achal Umtza v'Melach Mistarfin אכל אומצא ומלח מצטרפין. Achal Umtza v'Melach Mistarfin.
Now what is considered, you know, food and what's considered non-food and
what's considered food and what's considered liquid because we learned that food
and liquid don't combine. So he says Achal Umtza אכל אומצא, Achal
Umtza, if you ate like raw meat with the salt on it,
that combines. So maybe salt by itself not, that you know would
not be considered food. That we'll see a little bit later. V'af
al gav d'lav achila hee ואף על גב דלאו אכילה היא, V'af
al gav d'lav achila hee,
even though eating salt is not, that, is not eating, kevan d'achli
inshi mistarfin כיון דאכלי אינשי מצטרפין. Kevan d'achli inshi mistarfin. Since people
eat this together, presumably seems to be the point. Therefore they combine,
so in this context it becomes part of the food. Mistarfin מצטרפין.
Mistarfin.
Salted
raw meat?
Salted raw meat.
Like a beef jerky?
It's, but well, it's like beef tartare or something. It's not maybe.
That's not... yeah, but if it gets absorbed in
something else, do you consider it like you know you consider them
almost as two separate things? You know what I'm saying? Because you
could say like you know if it's sitting in marinade would you
say the marinade...
well
we're going to talk about that, so let's keep on reading. Okay,
Amar Reish Lakish אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, Tzir al gabi
yerek mistaref ציר על גבי ירק מצטרף. Tzir al gabi yerek mistaref.
The juice, the sauce that's on a vegetable combines even though you
don't call one a food and the other a liquid. L'chigrogoret b'Yom
HaKippurim לכגרוגרת ביום הכיפורים L'chigrogoret b'Yom HaKippurim for the minimum size of
a kigrogoret כגרוגרת. Kigrogoret.
Does Tzir ציר Tzir mean, does Tzir mean Tzir Dagim davka ציר
דגים דוקא? Tzir Dagim davka?
No, Rashi רש״י Rashi seems to say here that Tzir ציר Tzir
means the juices from the cooking of it. Where's Rashi רש״י? Rashi?
Matka u'mateka d'ochla מתקא וממתקא דאכלא, Matka u'mateka d'ochla, how he explains
it
next.
So okay, some type of a sauce. Peshita פשיטא. Peshita. No, mahu
d'teima maski hu מהו דתימא משקה הוא, Mahu d'teima maski hu, it's
a liquid, the Tzir ציר. Tzir. Ka Mashma Lan kol shurei ochla
ochla hu קא משמע לן כל שורי אוכלא אוכלא הוא. Ka Mashma
Lan kol shurei ochla ochla hu. Anything coming to improve to the
food is considered a type of a food. So if you eat
like some meat with sauce, you know mashed potatoes with sauce, it's
not meat and
liquid, it's
actually all considered food and it combines.
Amar Reish Lakish אמר ריש לקיש. Amar Reish Lakish. But yes, that
already makes sense sometimes with
Shabbos שבת Shabbos where you're eating food. Yeah, that actually is an
issue by Shabbos שבת Shabbos as well because when we talk about
bishul achar bishul b'lach בישול אחר בישול בלח, Bishul achar bishul b'lach,
we talk about well let's say the dish is part solid and
part liquid and we actually do somewhat categorize that based on ikar
v'tafel עיקר וטפל, Ikar v'tafel, so there's related issues there. But it
works the other way
around with like soup with whatever it is then it's considered a
liquid?
It's an interesting question. I don't know. It's an interesting question. Yeah,
it's an interesting question also because right to what degree is soup
a liquid? You know if you have vegetable soup would that go
under melo lugmav מלא לוגמיו Melo lugmav or would that go under
kigrogoret כגרוגרת? Kigrogoret?
If you went to a restaurant and asked for something to drink
and they gave you soup...
unless you get soup in a cup. That's an interesting question how
soup would be categorized.
And one quick question. When we say a Kizayit כזית, Kizayit, does
it mean
like it's approximately like a Kizayit כזית? Kizayit? No, but a Kizayit
כזית.
Kizayit. The size of a Kizayit כזית. Kizayit. Not that you actually...
you're not eating an olive. You're eating an olive's worth. So that's
what the kaf כ Kaf means. Okay, so Amar Reish Lakish אמר
ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, Achal achila gassa b'Yom HaKippurim patur אכל
אכילה גסה ביום הכיפורים פטור. Achal achila gassa b'Yom HaKippurim patur. If
you eat a... overeat on Yom Kippur יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you're
totally stuffed and you're eating on Erev Yom Kippur ערב יום כיפור
Erev Yom Kippur and you keep on eating on Yom Kippur יום
כיפור Yom Kippur and you're just like forcing the food down. So
then you're exempt. Mai taama? Asher lo te'uneh מאי טעמא אשר לא
תעונה Mai taama? Asher lo te'uneh is
the... the one who does not afflict themselves. So prat l'mazik פרט
למזיק. Prat l'mazik. So we're talking about in some type of a
thing that is abates the sense of affliction. If your eating is
actually... is hurting you and there's a great little Rashi רש״י Rashi
here, four lines down in the wide lines, Rashi רש״י, Rashi, four
lines up from the from the bottom. Prat l'mazik פרט למזיק, Prat
l'mazik, l'zeh she'eino mitbatel mimenu shum inuy al yedei achila לזה שאינו
מתבטל ממנו שום עינוי על ידי אכילה. L'zeh she'eino mitbatel mimenu shum
inuy al yedei achila. So it excludes this type of person who's
eating and the eating does not do anything to abate the sense
of affliction. And then it says ella אלא, Ella, great line of
Rashi רש״י Rashi here, mazik hu et ha'ochlin v'et atzmo מזיק הוא
את האוכלין ואת עצמו. Mazik hu et ha'ochlin v'et atzmo. This type
of an eating is a waste of the food, it's hurting the
food and it's hurting you. It's not doing good to either of
you. It's wasting the food and it's... and it's hurting yourself.
But then he's eating in a normal eating to satiate stuff
before we got to that point? No, did that Erev Yom Kippur
ערב יום כיפור. Erev Yom Kippur. You don't eat up through achila
gassa אכילה גסה. Achila gassa. Erev Yom Kippur ערב יום כיפור Erev
Yom Kippur you filled yourself up and that was a normal achila
אכילה. Achila. Comes Yom Kippur יום כיפור Yom Kippur and the eating
you're doing on Yom Kippur יום כיפור Yom Kippur is only is...
is stuffing yourself. You already sated and now it's like you know...
no, it's like you know you had your Thanksgiving feast and you
said I can't eat another bite and then you force yourself to
eat more on Yom Kippur יום כיפור... Yom Kippur... you know that
night even though you were totally stuffed.
If a non כהן Kohen ate תרומה Terumah אכילה גסה, Achila Gasa,
משלם את הקרן. meshalem et hakeren. Now if a
non כהן Kohen eats תרומה Terumah בשוגג, beshogeg, he pays, he pays
the תרומה Terumah back plus a fifth, actually it's a quarter, but
it's a fifth after you pay it like if it's, if it's
a hundred and you pay twenty-five, then a hundred and twenty-five is
now the twenty-five is a fifth of the total. So anyway, but
that's what he pays but only if he eats תרומה. Terumah. If
he destroys תרומה, Terumah, he only pays back the principal. So if
a זר zar eats תרומה Terumah אכילה גסה, achila gasa, same idea,
if he was totally stuffed and he forced the תרומה Terumah down,
משלם את הקרן, meshalem et hakeren, you only pay the principal, ואינו
משלם את החומש, ve'eino meshalem et hachomesh, not the additional fifth. It's
not, it doesn't constitute eating. כי יאכל, Ki yochal, it says, וכי
יאכל קודש בשגגה. vechi yochal kodesh bishgaga. יאכל, Yochal, it has to
be eating, פרט למזיק, prat lemazik, not this. This isn't considered eating,
this is considered damaging, damaging yourself. Now, of course, what would be
more interesting would be saying if you ate חלב, chelev,
you know, on אכילה גסה, achila gasa, you ate חמץ chametz אכילה
גסה. achila gasa. You know, these two things are also are not
like מאכלות אסורות. ma'achalot assurot. So, I mean תרומה Terumah I guess
is, but still, the difference of אכילה achila versus מזיק. mazik. And
you know, יום כיפור Yom Kippur is about abating the עינוי, inuy,
it's opposed to something which focuses on the highly problematic nature of
the object itself, like חלב, chelev, you know, and you're still putting
the חלב chelev into your body. But nevertheless, there tends to be
an assumption that the issues of אכילה גסה achila gasa as an
exemption would apply to those issues as well. Okay, so that's, I
mean, and there's other גמרות gemarot about, about אכילה, achila, אכל פרט
למזיק. achal prat lemazik. But here are two applications of very classic
examples of מאכלות אסורות. ma'achalot assurot. Okay. אמר רבי ירמיה אמר רבי
יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yirmya Amar Rabbi Yochanan, זר שכוסס שעורים. zar shekoses
se'orim.
Now we're going to other discussions of what is not, does or
does not constitute eating. If a non כהן Kohen chews barley. The
word כוסס koses is used particularly by like chewing raw grains in
a, you know, in a way that's not normally the way you
eat, you know, it's not normally edible. So if he chews raw
barley של תרומה, shel Terumah, משלם את הקרן ואינו משלם את החומש.
meshalem et hakeren ve'eino meshalem et hachomesh. Similarly
you pay the principal, but you don't pay a fifth cause that's
not considered an act of eating. כי יאכל פרט למזיק, Ki yochal
prat lemazik, when you eat as opposed to when you damage. Okay,
so presumably also would you say if you did the same on
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, although by יום כיפור Yom Kippur again, you
could have different categories. One is what defines an act of eating,
the other is, is it considered something that considers to be abating
the עינוי. inuy. So in theory, you could have different results to
that, right? That process is not a normal eating, but the result
is that it filled up your stomach. So we'll discuss that also
when we get to the...
Anatole? Am I over...
No, tobacco doesn't fill you. No, but anyway we'll see it when
we discuss the issue about אכילה שלא, achila shelo, about eating things
that are not normally eaten, which is the upcoming משנה. mishnah. Let's
get to the, I mean
let's get to the תוספות. Tosafot. אמר רב שיזבי אמר רבי יוחנן,
Amar Rav Shizbi Amar Rabbi Yochanan, זר שבלע שזיפין של תרומה, zar
shebala shezifin shel Terumah,
if a non כהן Kohen ate שזיפין. shezifin. What are שזיפין? shezifin?
Peaches? No, I think plums, right? Look at רש"י, Rashi, two lines
from the top. שזיפין, Shezifin, prunes, plums. Okay, so you swallowed a
prune whole. You didn't chew it is the point.
Okay, והקיאן, veheki'an, and he then regurgitated them, ואכלן אחר, va'achalan acher,
and another person ate the regurgitated plums.
So the reason it gives this example is cause it doesn't, if
it was chewed it would be more disgusting, but anyway it would
be less of a חידוש. chiddush. Here the idea is that the
other person could be eating, okay, it's disgusting, but still, a whole
thing, it's still a whole prune, you spit the whole thing back
out.
Okay, ראשון משלם קרן וחומש. rishon meshalem keren vechomesh. The first guy
pays principal and a fifth. That's considered eating. Even if you swallow
something whole, as opposed
to, as opposed to forced eating, as opposed to chewing raw grain,
swallowing whole still constitutes eating. Sometimes people swallow things whole. So the
first guy pays the principal and the fifth. שני, sheni, the second
guy, אינו משלם אלא דמי עצים לראשון בלבד. eino meshalem ela d'mei
etzim lerishon bilvad. Only pays back the first guy the cost of
firewood. What it means, it means the first guy, once he swallowed
it, he קונה koneh it. It became his. You know, if he
stole a כהן's Kohen תרומה, Terumah, but it's like, you know, there's
all these principles in בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, you steal something, you
change it, whatever, it says then you take possession of it. He
has to pay back the כהן, Kohen, but he took possession of
it. So he took possession of it, and therefore, A, so the
second guy's obligation is not going to be to the כהן, Kohen,
it's going to be to the first guy. And number two, it's
no longer considered food. Even though he, it's still a whole prune,
it's now disgusting and it's not considered food. So now it's considered
just like wood, like what can it be used for? What would
a normal person use this for? They'd use it for firewood, they'd
use it for fuel. No normal person would eat it. So therefore
the obligation is only to the first guy. Number one, the first
guy owns it. Number two, it's no longer food. It's only treated
as fuel. Now it's interesting to ask whether the second guy's exemption
is cause the first thing that was done was considered an אכילה
achila or not, right? To what degree are those two concepts, you
know, linked or not linked? Meaning, let's say the first guy who
swallowed it, swallowed it and it was an אכילה גסה. achila gasa.
So we already said that's not considered an אכילה, achila, right? And
so the first doesn't pay the כהן kohen more than the principal.
And then he spits it up. Is it also to the second
guy only considered like firewood? Is the reason it's considered to the
second guy no longer like food because the physical reality that it
was swallowed and regurgitated? Or, yes, or, but it's interesting the way
the גמרא gemara frames it is, it might be because halakhically we
say what the first guy did was an אכילה. achila. And therefore
that changes the status of this object vis-a-vis the second guy. So,
I'm just putting that out there.
How is it that regurgitating a piece of food is not מפקיר
mafkir that object so that the guy then takes it? How can
he be חייב chayav anything to that guy? Right? How can you
be חייב? chayav?
I don't know! Don't touch that prune, I'm planning on re-eating it!
No, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait! I'm here! I'm going to save
this gum for later, okay?
What do you want me to say? Alright, anyway, yes.
Is דמי עצים dmei etzim have to do with סוכה sukkah or
is that...?
It is true, it's a similar phrase.
It's used about a סוכה. sukkah.
Right, right, right. But that here just means that it's, it is
the same phrase, but here just means that, you know, most what
it is is just firewood and fuel. It doesn't have any value
other than that.
Also in terms of the way they term it like a fifth
and percentages, it's very confusing the way they're doing it. I know.
It's the opposite of the way we would do it.
Right, I know.
And anyone because when you say a hundred and you say
eight percent...
I understand, I understand. That, yes, that's why I always point it
out because it's exactly not what we would think. Okay. האוכל והשותה
אין מצטרפין. ha-ochel veha-shoteh ein mitztarfin. Now we already sort of referred
to this issue. Food and drink don't combine for the minimum size.
מאן תנא? man tana? Who is the author of the משנה? mishna?
Who is the תנא tanna that says that food and drink don't
combine for a minimum size? אמר רב חסדא במחלוקת שנויה. amar Rav
Chisda be-machloket shnuya. You're right to point that out, because it actually
is a matter of debate. רבי יהושע היא. Rabbi Yehoshua hi. And
it's רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua who says that they don't combine. דתנן,
detnan, we taught: כלל אמר רבי יהושע, klal amar Rabbi Yehoshua,
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said a principle: כל שטומאתו ושיעורו שוה מצטרף.
kol she-tumato ve-shiyuro shaveh mitztaref.
If the טומאה tumah and the degree of טומאה—he's tumah talking about
טומאה tumah purposes and not about יום כיפור Yom Kippur purposes—and the
minimum size are the same, they combine. So, if you have for
example a half of a כזית kezayit of נבילה neveilah
and another half of a כזית kezayit of a נבילה... neveilah... Okay
well that's too easy. If you have a half of a כזית
kezayit of נבילה, neveilah, let's see the example רש״י Rashi does, or
well actually no, that is the example רש״י Rashi does. Okay so
it is pretty straightforward because most things are different amounts of טומאה.
tumah. Okay, so then they combine. It doesn't matter if one is
from one animal carcass and the other from another animal carcass, they're
both the same minimum amount. How much נבילה neveilah do you need
for טומאה? tumah? א כזית. a kezayit. And they both have the
same degree of טומאה. tumah. If you touch it you're טמא tamei
for a day. So that does combine. That's
טומאתו ושיעורו שוה מצטרף. tumato ve-shiyuro shaveh mitztaref. Not much. טומאתו ולא
שיעורו שיעורו ולא טומאתו... tumato ve-lo shiyuro shiyuro ve-lo tumato... if there's
a difference on either plane, one,
you know, only the טומאה's tumah the same but not the amount.
What would be an example? נבילה neveilah and a שרץ. sheretz. Both
of them cause one day טומאה, tumah, but the minimum amount of
a נבילה neveilah is a size of an olive, the minimum amount
of a שרץ sheretz is a size of a lentil piece. So
in that case
they would not combine, even if you had a half of a
lentil bean of נבילה neveilah and a half of a lentil bean
of a שרץ, sheretz, the fact that they're different minimums puts them
in fundamentally different categories. Okay? That's
טומאתו ולא שיעורו. tumato ve-lo shiyuro. Or the שיעורו ולא טומאתו. shiyuro
ve-lo tumato. If it's the same amount but different types of טומאה.
tumah. You have a half of a כזית kezayit of נבילה neveilah
and a half of a כזית kezayit of a human corpse מת.
met. They both go by כזית, kezayit, but they're different degrees of
טומאה. tumah. א נבילה a neveilah causes one day טומאה, tumah, a
corpse causes seven days טומאה. tumah. So those also do not combine,
even for a one day טומאה. tumah. The fact that
there's different טומאה tumah or different minimums puts them in fundamentally different
categories, they can't combine.
Is the corpse not just a כלל, klal, any corpse or a
Jewish corpse? Any corpse.
The question about non-Jewish corpses is whether it's טומאה tumah in an
אהל, ohel, under a roof, but by contact... לא טומאתו ולא שיעורו,
lo tumato ve-lo shiyuro, certainly if neither the טומאה tumah nor the
שיעור shiur is the same, אין מצטרפין, ein mitztarfin, they don't combine.
So as long as there's any point of difference in terms of
טומאה tumah or the amount, they don't combine even for the more
lenient category. So, and that is presumed, that is debated. That's רבי
יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua position. So the חכמים, chachamim, the implicit חכמים chachamim
would say that even across those lines they can combine, at least
for the more lenient category. Right? So a half a כזית kezayit
of a מת meit and a half a כזית kezayit of a
נבילה neveilah maybe combine for a one day טומאה, tumah, not a
seven day טומאה, tumah, but a one day טומאה, tumah, right? So
only רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says that these categories do not combine
across the lines. But Nachman says no. אפילו תימא רבנן, afilu tema
Rabbanan, even the רבנן Rabbanan who there say they do combine across
categories, here would agree. עד כאן לא קאמרי רבנן התם, ad kan
lo kamrei Rabbanan hatam, only there the רבנן Rabbanan argue with רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua ענין טומאה, inyan tumah, when it comes to טומאה,
tumah, דשם טומאה חד היא, deshem tumah chad hi, they'll say, look,
as long as it's all טומאה, tumah, it doesn't matter if it
goes across categories of minimum
amount, especially in a case where the effect is the same. So
like a half of a of a of a barley bean of
a of a lentil bean of of נבילה neveilah and a half
of a lentil bean of a שרץ sheretz could combine to cause
a one day טומאה tumah because נבילה neveilah causes a one day
טומאה tumah and a שרץ sheretz causes a one day טומאה. tumah.
So have them at least combine you know for the for the
minimum amount. I think I said that wrong. A half of a
no I think I said that right. No. A half of a
כזית kezayit of a שרץ. sheretz. That that would be the makeweight.
Anyway, a half of a כזית kezayit of a שרץ sheretz and
a half of a כזית kezayit in a נבילה. neveilah. Anyway, either
way as long as you're doing it to be more to be
more strict, not to be more lenient, they could combine as long
as anyway it's the same amount of טומאה. tumah. אבל הכא aval
hacha here משום יתובי דעתא היא. mishum yisuvay da'ata hi. The problem
is not just a formalistic saying of oh you know you have
some from category A and some from category B and they're one
is more strict anyway so of course it can combine. Here it's
a practical question of does it abate the sense of
affliction? והאי לא מיתבא דעתא vehai lo meisyava da'ata and you know
a food below the threshold plus drink below the threshold doesn't do
it for you even in some formalistic way you say you have
a minimum amount. It doesn't have the same effect of abating the
sense of עינוי inuy which seems to be something the גמרא Gemara
falls back on you know to explain like a number of differences
here. It makes it much more subjective and reality based as we
discussed yesterday than many of these discussions in other contexts. וכן אמר
ריש לקיש במחלוקת שנויה. vechen amar Reish Lakish bemachloket shnuya. Reish Lakish
says no it's the same debate. It's only רב יהושע Rav Yehoshua
by טומאה tumah who says things don't combine across categories that would
say food and drink don't combine on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. רב
יהושע Rav Yehoshua דתנן כלל אמר רבי יהושע detnan klal amar Rabbi
Yehoshua said. ורבי יוחנן אמר אפילו תימא רבנן veRabbi Yochanan amar afilu
teima rabbanan it's even the רבנן. rabbanan. עד כאן לא קאמרי רבנן
התם ad kan lo kaamrei rabbanan hatam only by טומאה tumah אבל
הכא משום יתובי דעתא הוא. aval hacha mishum yisuvay da'ata hu.
There by טומאה tumah the רבנן rabbanan say okay you could take
something from a strict category and combine it for a more lenient
category and get the minimum amount. But here it's about settling the
דעת. da'at. It's about abating the affliction. והאי לא קא מיתבא דעתא
vehai lo ka meisyava da'ata and a little bit and food and
drink even though they're both point you know just an epsilon below
the threshold it doesn't combine. You need to hit the threshold of
each one in order to achieve that sense of removing the affliction.
So basically from a formalistic sense if you have a strict thing
right like like the שרץ sheretz is stricter because שרץ sheretz causes
טומאה tumah even with a lesser amount. And it causes but both
שרץ sheretz and a נבילה neveilah cause one day טומאה. tumah. So
if you have a נבילה neveilah minus epsilon of a כזית kezayit
and you take a little שרץ sheretz why not combine? שרץ sheretz
is stricter, both one day טומאה, tumah, so you can have a
little שרץ sheretz add to the amount of נבילה neveilah and cause
the טומאה. tumah. That's what the רבנן rabbanan say. Fine. That's when
it's only a formalistic question of minimums and categories of נבילה. neveilah.
But here it's the question of your psychological reality and the impact
it has and here we're claiming there it has to be food
by itself or drink by itself. A little bit of each is
not going to affect the same reality. So again you could debate
whether or not that's true but the fascinating thing is that the
גמרא Gemara is not saying this is not just the formalistic type
of an approach that we have by other things. This very much
is rooted in the actual psychological reality that is
affected here.
Raising interesting questions. Let's say I eat things most people don't so
it satisfies me then most people it's not אכילה. achila. Right.
So let's take a look at the next משנה. Mishnah. Right. So
there's two questions. One is one is subjective. The subjective aspect we
dealt with was מלא לוגמיו. melo lugmav. That's even getting it to
be more like non-formalistic. Every person we're going to assess differently. So
you say oh if you assess the minimum amount differently let's say
you you know let's say different foods do different things for me.
You know the גמרא Gemara sort of tries to deal with that.
Is בשר basar the same as as you know as grape leaves
or whatever? So there's obviously some balance between the subjective and trying
to get some type of a standard or trying to claim that
the standard is true regardless of the subjectivity. But that aspect of
subjective we only found by minimum amounts. We do not find it
by things like the types of food. Okay. So there's but it's
still different to say it's rooted in an in an actual psychological
reality without saying it's subjective. We could still say as we assess
what that standard psychological reality is. Right. It does not have to
be each a different rule for each person. But there still is
a difference between saying completely formalistic as opposed to rooted in a
psychological reality. But even saying psychological reality could be a standard psychological
reality. So it's a completely next step to say as we assess
it for each individual person which the גמרא Gemara only did when
it came to the quantity and there only by the drink and
not by the food.
If I eat things most people don't eat then...
Right. And that actually is a perfect segue into the next משנה.
Mishnah. אכל ושתה בהעלם אחד אינו חייב אלא חטאת אחת. achal veshashata
be'e'lem echad eino chayav ela chatat achat. Now here's one area in
which food and drink do somewhat combine not to the minimum amounts
but to the same עבירה. aveira. If somebody ate a minimum amount
and drank a minimum amount and they did it in one state
of forgetfulness they forgot it was יום כיפור Yom Kippur you only
bring one קרבן. korban. Because basically let's say you ate let's say
you ate you know two ככותבות. kekotevot. in one state of forgetfulness
it would only bring one קרבן. korban. That's considered to be one
עבירה. aveira. You just did more of the עבירה. aveira. Okay, like
the גמרא Gemara says if a נזיר nazir forgot he was a
נזיר nazir and he's drinking wine the whole day, as long as
he doesn't remember anywhere in the middle that he's a נזיר, nazir,
it's considered to be one—after a while he won't remember—it's considered to
be one עבירה aveira done, you know, multiple times as opposed to
multiple עבירות. aveirot. So, and therefore here, well, or an ongoing... yeah,
but for קרבן korban purposes, right, well it is true that normally
we say things have to be like בכדי אכילת פרס bechdei achilat
pras to be considered a continuous process, but at least it's not
a separate, distinct enough. So I wouldn't go so far to say
it's just one continuous thing. That would be like if it's בכדי
אכילת פרס, bechdei achilat pras, בכדי שתיית רביעית. bechdei shtiyat revi'it. But
even if it's over at different moments, it's not distinct enough from
the other one, it's that it brings a separate קרבן. korban. In
the end it would only bring one קרבן. korban. In the case
by a נזיר nazir where it's not a קרבן, korban, it'd only
be one set of מלקיות malkiyot if you actually talked because if
you warned him... okay, that's different anyway because if you warned him
then the warning should—I'm not going to get into that, even though
I may have raised it. Anyway, okay, but it's enough that those
two things, even if you don't call them one act, combine for
one קרבן korban because there's the same עבירה. aveira. Okay, the same
עבירה, aveira, not done—the עבירה aveira of לא תעונה, lo te'uneh, of
not abating the affliction. It's the same prohibition even though one is
through eating, one is through drinking, and even though the minimums don't
combine, nevertheless it's the same עבירה aveira done without being aware in
between, it's only one קרבן. korban. Okay, however, אכל ועשה מלאכה, achal
ve'asah melacha, חייב שתי חטאות. chayav shtei chatatot. If you eat and
do מלאכה, melacha, those are two separate prohibitions, one is לא תעונה
lo te'uneh and the other is לא תעשה כל מלאכה. lo ta'aseh
kol melacha. So there, even if it was one forgetting of יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, two separate categories of prohibition, two קרבנות. korbanot. אכל
אוכלין שאינם ראוים, achal ochlin she'einam re'uyim, now this is going back
to Michael's question, let's say you ate food that is not fit
for being eaten, לאכילה, le'achila, ושתו משקין שאינם ראוים לשתיה, veshatu mashkin
she'einam re'uyim lishtiya, or liquid that's not fit for being... non-potable, ושתה
ציר או מורייס, veshata tzir o moryes, and this is presumably an
example of not fit for drink, you drank fish brine or מורייס.
moryes. How do they translate
מורייס? moryes? Fish fat. There you go. פטור, patur, you are exempt.
So that presumably is an example of לא ראוי לשתיה. lo ra'uy
lishtiya.
Just as it goes through it's out? Exactly. אמר ריש לקיש, amar
Reish Lakish,
סבר ריש לקיש, savar Reish Lakish, מפני מה—all mipnei mah right, let's
wait to see how the גמרא Gemara does it. אמר ריש לקיש,
amar Reish Lakish, says ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish,
מפני מה לא נאמרה אזהרה בעינוי? mipnei mah lo ne'emra azhara be'inui?
Now what the גמרא's Gemara has to now deal with is, you
know, the beginning of the פרק perek discussed how do we know
that, you know, לא תעונה, lo te'uneh, how do you... עינוי inui
means eating and drinking, how do we know the other עינויים? inuyim?
But now we're dealing with more technical problem, not just how do
we know the תורה's Torah mandating you not to eat and drink,
but in order to bring a קרבן, korban, you cannot bring a
קרבן korban or get מלקות malkot without a אזהרה, azhara, without a
negative prohibition. Right, that's the general rule. So even things that are
like weighty that you get כרת karet for, like not doing a
ברית מילה brit milah or not doing a קרבן פסח, korban pesach,
since it's not doing a positive מצוה mitzvah rather than transgressing a
negative, you don't bring a קרבן korban for not bringing קרבן פסח.
korban pesach. Okay, to bring a קרבן korban has to be two
things. Number one, you get כרת, karet, but number two, you have
to transgress a negative prohibition. To get מלקות, malkot, you need to
transgress a negative prohibition. So okay, the גמרא's Gemara now asking the
following question: we know you're obligated to fast and it means don't
eat and drink because it says ועניתם את נפשותיכם. ve'initem et nafshoteichem.
But we got a little bit of a problem. ועניתם את נפשותיכם
ve'initem et nafshoteichem is a positive מצוה. mitzvah. You shall fast. And
if I don't do it, so I haven't done a positive
מצוה. mitzvah. That means if you haven't done the positive מצוה mitzvah
of fasting, where does the תורה Torah ever say "don't do X"?
And if you want to make me bring a קרבן, korban, you
have to tell me "don't do X". So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
is going to say, you know, it was grammatically impossible for the
תורה Torah to say that, so it's as if the תורה Torah
did say it. So let's take a look at what ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish said. אמר ריש לקיש, amar Reish Lakish, מפני מה לא
נאמרה אזהרה בעינוי, mipnei mah lo ne'emra azhara be'inui, why does the
תורה Torah never exactly say "don't" by the issue of fasting? משום
דלא אפשר, mishum dela efshar, it's not possible to actually articulate that.
Okay, היכי נכתוב? heichi nictov? What do you want the תורה Torah
to say? נכתוב רחמנא nictov rachmana לא יאכל, lo yochal, don't eat
on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? אכילה בכזית, achila bechazayit, as we've been
discussing, it's not—no, then it would have meant an olive's worth, right?
And we know it's about affliction and non-affliction, and it's about ככותבת.
kekotavet. So it could not have used the verb "eat," that would
not have been the right verb to use. Okay, אכילה בכזית. achila
bechazayit.
נכתוב רחמנא, nictov rachmana, let the תורה Torah say לא תעונה, lo
te'uneh, don't fast? No, קום אכול ושתה, kum echol ushtei, that means
eat, that's saying the opposite. Okay. So what it really needs to
say is "don't not fast." So anyway, מתיב ליה רב הושעיא, mative
lei Rav Hoshaia, רב הושעיא Rav Hoshaia challenges: נכתוב רחמנא nictov rachmana
הישמר פן לא תעונה, hishamer pen lo te'uneh, guard yourself lest you
do not fast, which is another way of saying "don't"... Fast? No,
קומו ואכלו *Kumu Ve’echlu*, that means eat! That’s saying the opposite! Okay,
so what it really needs to say is don’t not fast. So
anyway, מתיב רב הושעיה *Mativ Rav Oshaya*, Rav Oshaya challenges, נכתוב רחמנא
השמר פן לא תענה *Nichtov Rachmana Hishamair Pen Lo Se’aneh*, guard yourself
lest you do not fast, which is another way of saying don’t
not fast. So he says no, אם כן הוי פשיטא ליה *Im
kein havei pishita lei*, no, cause then השמר *Hishamair* and פן *Pen*
would mean two לאוין *Lavin*, and maybe the תורה Torah *Torah* only
wants to say one לאו *Lav*. And השמר לא תענה *Hishamair Lo
Se’aneh* that’s just not grammatically correct. So there’s no way to say
it, so it’s as if it said it, but it didn’t say
it cause it couldn't exactly say those words.
So מתיב רב ביבי בר אביי *Mativ Rav Bibi bar
Abaye*, so רב ביבי בר אביי *Rav Bibi bar Abaye*, yeah השמר
*Hishamair* and פן *Pen* would count as two, and somehow just to
say השמר לא תענה *Hishamair Lo Se’aneh* would not grammatically make sense.
So you’re backwards, like the תורה Torah *Torah* could not grammatically phrase
something in rabbinic categories.
That’s one way of saying it. That’s one way of saying it.
Okay. How about just say don’t not, don’t not to, לא לא
תענה *Lo lo se’aneh*? Okay, anyway, where
there’s of course that great line by Bruce Stanley Morgenbesser, he was
a philosopher at Columbia, anyway, he was known for his one-liners. So
somebody was giving a lecture once and said it’s very strange, you
know, in English a double negative is a positive, but a double
positive isn’t a negative. So he said yeah, yeah. Okay.
Anyway. All right. So אם כן הוי פשיטא ליה *Im kein havei
pishita lei*, so מתיב רב ביבי בר אביי *Mativ Rav Bibi bar
Abaye*, so רב ביבי בר אביי *Rav Bibi bar Abaye*, נכתוב רחמנא
השמר במצות עינוי inuy *Nichtov Rachmana Hishamair Bemitzvat Inuy*. Why doesn’t the
תורה Torah *Torah* itself say guard yourself regarding the מצוה *Mitzvah* of
fasting? Okay, so the guard makes it a לא תעשה *Lo Sa’aseh*.
No, אם כן השמר דלאו לאו השמר דעשה עשה *Im kein, hishamair
delav lav, hishamair de’aseh aseh*. No, that won’t work, because השמר *Hishamair*
when applied to השמר *Hishamair* to not do X makes it a
negative prohibition, but השמר *Hishamair* to do X means it’s an extension
of the positive. So adding השמר *Hishamair* to a to-do just extends
the idea of a positive, does not make it into a negative.
So מתיב רב אשי *Mativ Rav Ashi*, so רב אשי *Rav Ashi*
says how about this? נכתוב אל תסור מן העינוי *Nichtov Al Tasur
Min Ha’inuy*. Why doesn’t it say do not turn away from the
fasting? All right, תיקו *Teiku*, that’s difficult. But the upshot being that
there’s no good way to elegantly frame the idea of fasting without
using positive language, but somehow nevertheless we assume that the תורה *Torah*
wants to prohibit the opposite, and therefore we can make it, we
have the idea that there is a negative prohibition even though it’s
not written. Like the negative prohibition is implied, and that allows us
to have the idea that you bring a קרבן *Korban* if you
do eat or you would get מלקות *Malkos* because the negative prohibition
is implied even though it’s not really possible to elegantly state it.
Okay, so now we’re not done though with this issue. So let’s
take a look. דתנא מייתי לה מהכא *Detana meiti lah mehacha*, the
author of the ברייתא baraita. *Braisa*, the author of the ברייתא baraita,
*Braisa* doesn’t just say oh it’s implied because there’s no way to
say it, he learns out the idea of a negative prohibition from
the following דרשה drasha *Derasha*. ועניתם את נפשותיכם וכל מלאכה Melacha. לא
תעשה *Ve’inisem es nafshoseichem vechol melacha lo sa’asu*. Okay, afflict yourselves, do
no מלאכה Melacha. *Melacha*. So first it starts like this. יכול יהא
ענוש על תוספת tosefet. מלאכה Melacha *Yachol yehei anush al tosefes melacha*.
Wait a minute, maybe you will get punished for doing מלאכה Melacha
*Melacha* in the period of the תוספת tosefet. *Tosefes*. We’re going to
learn soon, and by the way, according to some ראשונים Rishonim, *Rishonim*,
the only place there’s a biblical מצוה *Mitzvah* of תוספת tosefet. *Tosefes*
of adding on to שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* and יום טוב Yom Tov,
*Yom Tov*, we assume it applies by all, but
according to some ראשונים *Rishonim*, biblically the מצוה *Mitzvah* of adding on
only is on יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur*, according to the
רמב"ם Rambam, *Rambam*. So let's say you started יום כיפור Yom Kippur,
*Yom Kippur* early because of the מצוה *Mitzvah* of תוספת tosefet *Tosefes*,
מוסיפין מחול על הקודש *Mosifin meichol al hakodesh*, you add from the
weekday, and during that period of תוספת tosefes *Tosefes* before it became
sunset you ate, or in that period of תוספת tosefes. *Tosefes* you
did מלאכה Melacha. *Melacha*, how bad is that עבירה *Aveira* if you
did it during the תוספת tosefes, *Tosefes*? So that’s where the ברייתא
*Braisa* starts. יכול יהא ענוש על תוספת tosefes. מלאכה Melacha. *Yachol yehei
anush al tosefes melacha*, maybe you get the punishment for doing מלאכה
Melacha *Melacha* during the period of the תוספת tosefes. *Tosefes*. תלמוד לומר
וכל הנפש אשר תעשה כל מלאכה Melacha בעצם היום הזה b'etzem hayom
hazeh. *Talmud lomar vechol hanefesh asher sa’aseh kol melacha be’etzem hayom hazeh*.
If you do מלאכה Melacha. *Melacha* in the essence of this day.
על עיצומו של יום הוא נכרת *Al itzumo shel yom hu nichras*,
you get כרת kareth *Kares* for doing מלאכה Melacha *Melacha* during the
day itself, ואינו ענוש כרת kareth על תוספת tosefes. *Ve’eino anush kares
al tosefes*, not during the add-on part of the day when you
started יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* early.
Also when you ended it, right?
Well yeah, but we’ll get to that later. Okay. על תוספת tosefes,
מלאכה Melacha *Al tosefes melacha*. יכול לא יהא ענוש כרת kareth על
תוספת tosefes. מלאכה Melacha *Yachol lo yehei anush kares al tosefes melacha*,
fine, you don’t get punished for doing מלאכה Melacha *Melacha* during the
תוספת tosefes. *Tosefes*, אבל יהא ענוש כרת kareth על תוספת tosefes, עינוי
inuy *Aval yehei anush kares al tosefes inuy*, maybe you’ll get punished
for not fasting during the תוספת tosefes, *Tosefes*, meaning the same weighty
punishment, we can discuss what the punishment is, maybe it’s just the
ביטול *Bitul* of the positive מצוה *Mitzvah* of תוספת *Tosefes*, but maybe
you would get actually the same punishment, כרת kareth *Kares*. תלמוד לומר
*Talmud lomar*, it says the same language by fasting. כי כל הנפש
אשר לא תעונה בעצם היום הזה b'etzem hayom hazeh. *Ki kol hanefesh
asher lo se’uneh be’etzem hayom hazeh*, it says בעצם b'etzem *Be’etzem* by
fasting as well, ונכרתה *Venichresah*. על עיצומו של יום הוא נכרת *Al
itzumo shel yom hu nichras*, by the essence of the day, if
you eat during the day itself you get כרת kareth *Kares*, ואינו
ענוש על תוספת עינוי inuy *Ve’eino anush al tosefes inuy*, not if
you eat during the addition. Fine. יכול לא יהא בכלל עונש onesh
*Yachol lo yehei bichlal onesh*, fine, maybe you don’t get כרת kareth,
*Kares* for eating and doing מלאכה Melacha *Melacha* during the תוספת *Tosefes*,
אבל יהא מוזהר על תוספת מלאכה Melacha. *Aval yehei muzhar al tosefes
melacha*, maybe you transgress a negative prohibition, you transgress the לאו *Lav*
even if you don’t get כרת kareth, *Kares*. תלמוד לומר וכל מלאכה
Melacha לא תעשה בעצם *Talmud lomar vechol melacha lo sa’asu be’etzem*. It
says do not do any מלאכה Melacha. *melacha* in the essence of
this day. So again, notice the word בעצם *b'etzem* by the doing
מלאכה Melacha *melacha*, not just by the punishment, but by the doing.
על עיצומו של יום הוא מוזהר *Al itzumo shel yom hu muzhar*,
you're prohibited, you get a negative prohibition on the essence of the
day, ואינו מוזהר על תוספת מלאכה Melacha *ve'eino muzhar al tosefet melacha*,
but you do not transgress the negative prohibition if you do it
during the תוספת *tosefet*, the add-on part of the day. יכול יהיה
מוזהר על תוספת מלאכה Melacha ואין מוזהר על תוספת עינוי inuy *Yachol
yehei muzhar al tosefet melacha v'ein muzhar al tosefet inuy*? Fine, maybe
you won't transgress for doing מלאכה Melacha *melacha* during the תוספת *tosefet*,
but maybe you'll transgress for not fasting. You won't get כרת kareth
*kares*, but maybe you'll transgress. ודינו *V'dinu*, and actually it's a קל
וחומר kal vachomer. *kal v'chomer* that I should say that I can
learn out that you should not transgress. ומה מלאכה Melacha שנוהגת בשבתות
וימים טובים *U'mah melacha she'noheget b'shabbatot v'yamim tovim*, מלאכה melacha *melacha* which
is more universal, it applies on שבת Shabbat *Shabbat* and ימים טובים
*Yomim Tovim*, אינה מוזהרת עליה *eina muzhara aleha*, you don't transgress during
the תוספת *tosefet* period. עינוי inuy? שאינו נוהג בשבתות וימים טובים אינו
דין שלא יהא מוזהר עליו *Inuy she'eino noheg b'shabbatot v'yamim tovim eino
din she'lo yehei muzhar alav*? So fasting which is not universal, it
only applies on יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*, so therefore it's
fundamentally a weaker prohibition, how much more so should you not transgress
during the תוספת *tosefet*. Okay, so therefore I could learn it out
from a קל וחומר *kal v'chomer*. So I know, we'll get to
it. Okay, so I could learn out now, I know that you
don't get כרת kareth, *kares* for תוספת *tosefet*, I know you don't
get a negative prohibition for תוספת *tosefet* because it says עצם etzem
*etzem*, the עיצומו של יום *itzumo shel yom*, and I know even
that the eating during the תוספת *tosefet* you don't transgress because of
a קל וחומר *kal v'chomer*. But now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, the
ברייתא *braita* continues. אבל אזהרה azharah לעינוי של יום עצמו לא למדנו
*Aval azhara l'inuy shel yom atzmo lo lamadnu*. But with all of
that saying what you don't get during the תוספת *tosefet*, we have
yet to learn out the negative prohibition of eating on יום כיפור
Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur*. Where is the negative prohibition to eat on
יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*? מניין *Minayin*, where do you know
that from? לא יאמר אינו עונש במלאכה *Lo yomar eino onesh b'melacha*.
Because here's the reason. Why did it have to say that there's
a punishment for this כרת kareth *kares* for doing מלאכה *melacha* on
יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*? Don't you, you don't need to
say that. דגמר מעינוי *D'gamar mei'inuy*, I could have learned it out
from the punishment from not fasting. ומה עינוי inuy? שאינו נוהג בשבתות
וימים טובים *U'mah inuy she'eino noheg b'shabbatot v'yamim tovim*, similar to the
קל וחומר *kal v'chomer* we said before, עינוי inuy. *inuy* which is
not universal, doesn't apply to שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat* and ימים טובים *Yomim
Tovim*, ענוש כרת kareth *anush kares*, you get כרת kareth. *kares*. מלאכה
שנוהגת בשבתות וימים טובים לא כל שכן *Melacha she'noheget b'shabbatot v'yamim tovim
lo kol sheken*? How much more so should you get כרת kareth
*kares* for doing מלאכה *melacha*? So למה נאמר lama neemar? *lamah ne'emar*,
so why did the תורה *Torah* have to tell me you get
מלאכה *melacha*, you get כרת kareth *kares* for doing מלאכה *melacha*? למה
נאמר מופנה mufne, *Lamah ne'emar mofneh*, to tell you actually you're right,
that to tell you you get כרת kareth *kares* by מלאכה *melacha*
is superfluous, you could have figured it out yourself. So להקיש *l'hakish*,
and the reason it's superfluous is in order to be a basis
for linking to the idea of fasting. ולדון ממנו גזירה שוה g'zeirah
shavah? *V'ladun mimenu gezeirah shava*, to make a, to make an equation.
נאמר עונש בעינוי ונאמר עונש במלאכה neemar onesh b'inuy v'neemar onesh b'melacha.
*Ne'emar onesh b'inuy v'ne'emar onesh b'melacha*. It tells you the punishment by
fasting, כרת *kares*, it tells you the punishment by מלאכה *melacha*, כרת
*kares*. Now we said the punishment by מלאכה *melacha* is superfluous, so
the fact that it's superfluous lets you use it as a funnel
to learn out other things. מה מלאכה לא ענש אלא ela אם
כן הזהיר *Mah melacha lo onash ella im ken hizhir*, so the
same way by מלאכה *melacha* we know not only is there the
punishment כרת *kares*, but there's also the negative prohibition, don't do מלאכה
*melacha*. אף עינוי inuy לא ענש אלא אם כן הזהיר *Af inuy
lo onash ella im ken hizhir*. So the same is true by
עינוי inuy *inuy*, the same way there's a punishment there's also a
prohibition. So, a big Mike's got to say, but just so what
did we say until now? The first part of the ברייתא *braita*
is not really relevant to us, it introduces the idea of תוספת
*tosefet*, there's an idea of adding onto יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom
Kippur*, tells us you don't get כרת *kares* or you don't transgress
for the תוספת *tosefet*. The second part of the ברייתא *braita* is
what's interesting to us. It says how do you know that there's
a negative prohibition to do מלאכה *melacha* on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
*Yom Kippur*? And it's not saying because here's the words in the
פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, there are no words in the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*.
It's basically saying the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* teaches you there's a negative
prohibition by linking fasting to מלאכה *melacha*. And saying the same way
fasting you get כרת *kares* and מלאכה *melacha* you get כרת *kares*,
so the same way there's כרת *kares* for, the כרת *kares* for
מלאכה *melacha* is backed by a negative prohibition, the כרת *kares* for
eating, that not fasting, is also backed by a negative prohibition. And
we're entitled to make that equation because we say it didn't have
to, it was superfluous to mention כרת *kares* by by מלאכה *melacha*,
I could have figured it out, so since it was superfluous the
purpose is to link it to eating and to teach me the
כרת *kares* by מלאכה *melacha* is backed by fasting by prohibition so
the כרת *kares* by eating is also backed by a negative prohibition.
Yes?
Wait, we're getting, we're getting back to this.
No, there's מילה *milah* and פסח *Pesach*, it's not backed by a
negative prohibition. Those are the only. Yes, but how do you know?
How do you know? Maybe this is only a, similar, maybe it's
only a positive? How do you know there's a negative prohibition?
Yeah. Can we go back to the אזהרה azharah *azhara* on עינוי
inuy *inuy*? Don't we have a principle sometimes that the reason why
something is mentioned twice is one is עונש *onesh* and one is
עונש *onesh*? So why don't we apply it here? I mean, the
words אזהרה azharah, *azhara* for killing is the same thing. לא תרצח
*Lo tirtzach*, how would you say it, don't not not kill?
What? I mean, no, that is an אזהרה azharah. *azhara*, don't kill.
No, but the אזהרה *azhara* for it?
In other words, לא תרצח *lo tirtzach* is
the אזהרה *azhara*, don't kill. But then what's the אזהרה *azhara* for?
No, the problem here is that it's only said in a positive,
fast. It's never said in a negative. Everything else is a negative.
Don't kill, don't lie, don't cheat, don't eat טרף, don't
do this, don't do that. But still, the fact that it's mentioned
twice, so haven't we have a principle of sometimes... one אזהרה and
one...
Yeah, but but not to turn a positive into a negative. No,
that's exactly the problem, yes. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, so that's how we learn it out because of the comparison
to the to the מלאכה.
So the גמרא Gemara says five lines down in the wide lines.
איכא למיפרך, ika mifrach, one minute, you can challenge that. מה עינוי
שלא הותר מכללו? ma inuy shelo hutar miklala? No,
you can't just say that that
it's a קל וחומר. If you get כרת for fasting, you get
כרת for for מלאכה. No, maybe עינוי inuy is more strict even
though it's not universal. Why is עינוי inuy. more strict? Because it's
never allowed, I mean outside of פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. תאמר במלאכה
שהותרה מכללה. tomar b'melacha shehutar miklala.
מלאכה sometimes is overridden like when you do מלאכה in the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash on שבת Shabbat and on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur
So just because you get כרת for עינוי innui doesn't mean you
get כרת for מלאכה. So there goes your idea that it's superfluous.
So אלא fine, try it this way. לא יאמר עונש בעינוי. lo
yomar onesh b'inuy. Let's try the other way. Let's say the the
כרת by עינוי innui. is superfluous. So why did it have to
say כרת by עינוי? innui דגמר ממלאכה, digmar mimelacha, I should learn
it out from מלאכה. מה מלאכה שהותרה מכללה ענוש כרת, mah Melacha
shehutar miklala anush kareth,
so מלאכה that sometimes is allowed like on in the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash nevertheless you get
כרת, עינוי שלא הותר מכללו לא כל שכן, inuy shelo hutar miklala
lo kol shekein, how much more so should you should you get
כרת, it should be obvious. למה נאמר? So why does it have
to say כרת by עינוי? innui It's superfluous. מופנה, mufne in order
to open it up, להקיש וללמוד הימנו גזירה שוה, l'hakish ul'lamod mimenu
g'zeirah shavah, to make an equation. נאמר עונש בעינוי ונאמר עונש במלאכה.
מה מלאכה ענוש והזהיר, mah Melacha anush v'hizhir, the same to tell
you both of them get כרת, so the same way the כרת
by מלאכה is backed with a negative prohibition, אף עינוי ענוש והזהיר,
af inuy anush v'hizhir, the same by by the issue of fasting.
So it's the same point that כרת is superfluous except the גמרא
Gemara didn't want to say it's superfluous by מלאכה. Maybe מלאכה you
wouldn't have gotten כרת. Fine, it's superfluous by עינוי. innui I could
have learned עינוי innui from מלאכה as opposed to the reverse. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, איכא למיפרך. ika mifrach. That's not good
either. מה מלאכה שכן נוהג בשבת ויום טוב, mah Melacha shekein noheig
b'Shabbos v'Yom Tov, like you said earlier. There's ways in which עינוי
innui, is more strict, it's never overridden for the בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, but there's ways in which מלאכה is more strict. מלאכה is
a universal. תאמר בעינוי שאין נוהג בשבת ויום טוב. tomar b'inuy she'ein
noheig b'Shabbos v'Yom Tov. עינוי innui. doesn't apply in other cases. So
basically you cannot say that the idea of כרת is superfluous in
one of those to allow you to make this equation because you
couldn't have learned one from the other. Each one has its stringencies.
Okay, so basically we've been trying to say let's learn it out
from the fact that the עונש is backed by an אזהרה by
fasting by by מלאכה and one of those ideas of כרת is
superfluous. We could have figured it out. And the answer is it's
not superfluous. You couldn't have figured it out, so you don't have
the basis for making this equation.
Is a מופנה mufne, the same as גזירה שוה?
g'zeirah shavah Yes, but you can only make a גזירה שוה g'zeirah
shavah. when you have an extra word. If the word isn't so
you need to make it extra to allow us to do the
גזירה שוה. g'zeirah shavah, I see. So and the response is it's
not extra.
Okay, but if something is linked by גזירה שוה, g'zeirah shavah in
this case because of its מופנה, mufne, it has to be the
same in all aspects or only in that one aspect that's actually
being linked? Things that are linked by גזירה שוה g'zeirah shavah. are
have to be equal in all...?
No, no, it's completely חז"ל'ס Chazal's discretion what things they're learning out
from a גזירה שוה. gezeirah shava.
You're exercising that discretion.
Exactly. Okay. אמר רבינא, amar Ravina, so we're still the question about
how do you link the two. So האי תנא עצם עצם גמר.
hai tanna etzem etzem g'mar. התנא The tanna is not focusing on
the fact that the כרת is extra and that allows us to
make the link. He's focusing on the fact that the word עצם
etzem is extra, בעצם היום הזה. Of course the whole point of
ובעצם v'etzem before was to tell me that it didn't apply during
the תוספת. So the גמרא Gemara says מופנה, one of them has
to be extra. דאי לא מופנה, d'ilo mufne, again if it's not
extra, איכא למיפרך דפרכינא. ika mifrach d'varchina. You can say that you
can't make the link. So איי פנויי מופנה, ai pnu'ei mufne, which
one is extra? חמישה קראי כתיבי. chamisha k'ra k'tivei. It says five
times, בעצם היום הזה. במלאכה
כתיבי
במלאכה. b'Melacha k'tivei b'Melacha. It says by מלאכה. Actually no, it doesn't
say five times בעצם by מלאכה but it says five times don't
do מלאכה. חד לאזהרה דיממא, chad l'azharah d'yemama,
one to tell me don't do מלאכה in the day, וחד לאזהרה
דליליא, v'chad l'azharah d'leilya, once to tell me don't do מלאכה at
night, וחד לעונש דיממא, v'chad l'onesh d'yemama, one the punishment of the
day, וחד לעונש דליליא, v'chad l'onesh d'leilya, one the punishment of the
night, וחד לאפנויי, v'chad l'afnu'ei, and one פסוק pasuk is extra למיגמר
עינוי ממלאכה בין דיממא בין דליליא, l'migmar inuy mimelacha bein d'yemama bein
d'leilya,
in order to link the עינוי to מלאכה and tell me that
the same way again that by מלאכה there's a negative prohibition, there's
a negative prohibition by the עינוי. So you can open up your
חומש Chumash and do the counting but the basic point is we've
got an extra prohibition there and therefore that allows us to link
them. דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא, d'vei Rabbi Yishmael tanna, נאמר כאן עינוי,
neemar kan inuy, here's another way. So that way is just saying
the same way by מלאכה it's
backed by an אזהרה, same by
eating it's backed by an אזהרה.
No, here's the way. It says here עינוי and it says over
there עינוי. Okay, let's see what the over there is. מה להלן
לא ענש אלא אם כן הזהיר אף כאן לא ענש אלא אם
כן הזהיר. Ma lehalan lo anash ela im ken hizhir af kan
lo anash ela im ken hizhir. The same way there, okay, it's
backed by a negative prohibition. So that's what's the there? רש"י Rashi
says על דבר אשר ענה את אשת רעהו. al devar asher ina
et eshet re'ehu. Okay,
so that's talking about a case of rape. So when the תורה
describes rape and it says ענה, ina, right? So that type of
עינוי is backed by a negative prohibition, don't rape, so you don't
have forbidden sex. So here too the עינוי is backed by a
negative prohibition. So we're not learning עינוי from מלאכה from יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, we're learning general points when the תורה speaks about עינוי
it is about, it's a negative. Of course there's a difference. There
it's don't do עינוי, don't do this act of afflicting, don't do
this act of rape. Here it's do עינוי. ושמרת. Veshamarta.
Right, it's the same issue, right? Exactly. So okay, okay. רב אחא
בר יעקב אמר Rav Acha bar Yaakov amar יליף שבת שבתון משבת
בראשית. yalif Shabbat Shabbaton mi-Shabbat Bereishit.
No,
by יום כיפור Yom Kippur it says it is a day of
שבת שבתון Shabbat Shabbaton and by the normal weekday שבת Shabbat, it
says שבת שבתון, Shabbat Shabbaton, weekday, weekly שבת. Shabbat מה להלן לא
ענש אלא אם כן הזהיר אף כאן לא ענש אלא אם כן
הזהיר. Ma lehalan lo anash ela im ken hizhir af kan lo
anash ela im ken hizhir. The same way a normal שבת Shabbat
is backed by a negative prohibition, אף כאן לא ענש אלא אם
כן הזהיר, af kan lo anash ela im ken hizhir, here too
it's backed by a negative prohibition. רב פפא אמר, Rav Pappa amar,
רב פפא Rav Pappa says, הוא גופיה שבת איקרי. hu gufei Shabbat
ikrei. You don't have to say it's compared to שבת בראשית. Shabbat
Bereishit. The very fact that יום כיפור Yom Kippur. is called שבת,
Shabbat okay, that tells you that it's backed, that you can't do
things on it. Now again, it's not exactly clear to me how
different that is, because we know the concept of שבת Shabbat means
don't do certain things based on שבת בראשית. Shabbat Bereishit. He's just
sort of saying that it's not based on a גזירה שוה. It's
not you have the word שבת Shabbat, and the word שבת Shabbat
and you link it and you learn out a negative prohibition. He's
saying intrinsically the word שבת Shabbat carries with it the meaning of
don't do the opposite, don't destroy the שבת, Shabbat and therefore the
word שבת Shabbat tells you a negative prohibition.
Okay. דכתיב תשבתו שבתכם. Dechtiv tishpetu shabbatchem. You should rest on your
שבתות, shabbats, which is by יום כיפור. Okay. Now, בשלמא רב פפא
לא אמר כרב אחא בר יעקב, bishlama Rav Pappa lo amar ke-Rav
Acha bar Yaakov, we get why רב פפא Rav Pappa did not
want to say like רב אחא בר יעקב, Rav Acha bar Yaakov,
it's linked to the שבת Shabbat. of בראשית Bereishit and you learn
out the prohibition from the שבת Shabbat of
בראשית, Bereishit, which is what רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Acha bar
Yaakov said. דקרא דכתיב ביה בגופיה אתי. Dekra dichtiv bei begufei atei.
He'd rather say the word itself on יום כיפור of שבת Shabbat
carries the meaning of a negative prohibition, not because we borrow the
negative prohibition from שבת.
Shabbat Why wouldn't anyone want to say?
I know. Well, because since when does the word שבת Shabbat intrinsically
mean a negative prohibition? It's right, in a way, it's only because
of your analogy to שבת בראשית. Shabbat Bereishit. שב ואל תעשה.
Shev
ve-al ta'aseh.
Right, it's only because of your analogy to שבת בראשית. Shabbat Bereishit.
אלא רב אחא בר יעקב מאי טעמא לא אמר כרב פפא? Ela
Rav Acha bar Yaakov mai ta'ama lo amar ke-Rav Pappa? Why did
רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov say the words שבת
שבתון Shabbat Shabbaton is coming to tell you the negative, don't do,
don't do the opposite? So no, because he needs that פסוק pasuk
to tell you something else. מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, Miba'ei lei lekhadata ditenya,
you need it for which we teach in a ברייתא. ועניתם את
נפשותיכם בתשעה לחדש, Ve-innitem et nafshoteichem betisha lachodesh, you should afflict yourselves
on the ninth. יכול יתחיל ויתענה בתשעה. Yachol yatchil ve-yitaneh betisha. Now
this is going to be where we get this idea of תוספת.
Right, it says fast yourself, the פסוק pasuk is ועניתם את נפשותיכם
בתשעה לחדש בערב מערב עד ערב, ve-innitem et nafshoteichem betisha lachodesh ba-erev
me-erev ad erev, from the ninth at night, from evening to evening.
So it's going to bother the ברייתא, first of all that's a
very bizarre thing, since when does the תורה say, it doesn't say
keep שבת Shabbos from Friday from night to night. So why, you
know, it's the tenth day, the tenth day begins the night of
the ninth. Why does it say the ninth at night? So from
that they're going to learn that to some degree יום כיפור already
begins in the night, and that's what we're going to learn the
idea of תוספת. Okay. יכול יתחיל ויתענה בתשעה, Yachol yatchil ve-yitaneh betisha,
maybe literally יום כיפור begins on the ninth? תלמוד לומר בערב, Talmud
lomar ba-erev, no, in evening. אי בערב יכול משתחשך? I ba-erev yachol
mishetachshach? If it's in the evening, maybe only when it's fully dark?
You know, when it really the tenth day begins. תלמוד לומר בתשעה.
Talmud lomar betisha. Then why does it say the ninth? הא כיצד?
Ha keitzad? How do you reconcile this? מתחיל ומתענה מבעוד יום. Matchil
umitaneh mibod yom. You start a little bit from the day before.
מכאן שמוסיפין מחול על הקדש, Mikan shemosifin mechol al hakodesh, this is
the basis that you add from the weekday. And as I said,
generally we speak about like starting שבת Shabbos, early and adding of
שבת Shabbos, and יום טוב, Yom Tov. but according to some ראשונים,
the רמב"ם, Rambam the only biblical idea of תוספת is by יום
כיפור because of the פסוק of
בתשעה לחדש בערב. betisha lachodesh ba-erev. ואין לי אלא בכניסתו. Ve-ein li
ela bechnisato. I only know about adding and starting יום כיפור early
when it begins. ביציאתו מנין? Biytsi'ato minayin? How do I know you're
supposed to add a little bit even after יום כיפור, when it's
harder, you're dying to eat? תלמוד לומר מערב עד ערב, Talmud lomar
me-erev ad erev, from evening to evening. So the same way when
it began, it began a little bit into the day, when it
ends, it goes a little bit into the next day. ואין לי
אלא יום הכפורים. Ve-ein li ela Yom Hakippurim. Now here's where we
extend it from יום כיפור elsewhere. I only know
יום כיפור. שבתות מנין? Shebattot minayin? How do I know there's an
idea of תוספת שבת? tosefet Shabbat? תלמוד לומר תשבתו. Talmud lomar tishpetu.
Right, it says תשבתו שבתכם. tishpetu shabbatchem. שבתכם. shabbaskhem. ואין לי אלא
שבתות ימים טובים מנין תלמוד לומר שבתכם. Ve-ein li ela shabbasos, yamim
tovim minayin? Talmud lomar shabbaskhem. So the extra words תשבתו שבתכם tishbesu
shabbaskhem tells me this idea of תוספת applies even to שבת Shabbos,
and יום טוב. Yom Tov, As I said, רמב"ם Rambam thinks that
that's only דרבנן. derabbanan. הכיצד? Ha-keitzad? How is this possible? כל מקום
שנאמר שבות, Kol makom she-ne'emar shevus, wherever it says rest, מוסיפין מחול
על הקדש, mosifin me-chol al ha-kodesh, you add. So שבת, Shabbos, so
תשבתו שבתכם tishbesu shabbaskhem for רב פפא Rav Pappa teaches you that
it is a negative prohibition like שבת, but the other learning from
תשבתו שבתכם tishbesu shabbaskhem is to teach you that every שבת, whether
it's יום כפור, Yom Kippur, whether it's שבת, whether it's יום טוב,
starts a little bit from the day before. Okay. דתניא ועצם עצם
האי בתשעה לחדש מאי עביד ליה? De-tanya ve-etzem etzem hai be-tisha la-chodesh
mai avid leh? So on the עמוד א', amud alef, remember we
had a תנא tanna that said because it says עצם to teach
me you only get punished and you only transgress on the day
itself, not on the תוספת. So the גמרא Gemara is saying if
you're learning out that you don't get punished on the תוספת, you're
implicitly learning out that there is an idea of תוספת. So according
to him, you don't need the פסוק to teach me בתשעה לחדש
מערב עד ערב be-tisha la-chodesh me-erev ad erev that there's a concept
of תוספת. You can infer it from the fact that the פסוק
is telling you you don't get punished for the תוספת. You don't
get punished for the תוספת, but implicitly, there's an idea of תוספת.
So what do you do from בתשעה לחדש? be-tisha la-chodesh?
So what do you need that for? מיבעי ליה לכדתני חייא בר
רב מדפתי, Miba'ei leh le-khid-tani Chiyya bar Rav mi-Difti, what לחיא בר
רב מדפתי le-Chiyya bar Rav mi-Difti says. דתני רב חייא בר רב
מדפתי ועניתם את נפשותיכם בתשעה, De-tani Rav Chiyya bar Rav mi-Difti ve-innisem
es nafshoseikhem be-tisha, you should afflict yourselves on the ninth. וכי בתשעה
מתענין? Ve-khi be-tisha misa'nin? Do you really afflict yourselves on the ninth?
והלא בעשרה מתענין? Ve-halo be-asara misa'nin? The fast starts on the tenth.
So why does it say the ninth? So one answer is תוספת.
But if you already know the idea of תוספת, what is this
telling you? לומר לך כל האוכל ושותה בתשעה מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו
התענה תשיעי ועשירי. Lomar lekha kol ha-okhel ve-shoseh be-tisha ma'ala alav ha-kasuv
ke-illu his'anna tishii ve-asiri. This is a very other famous teaching. If
you eat on the ninth, you don't fast on the ninth, but
if you eat on the ninth, it's like you fasted. בתשעה לחדש,
Be-tisha la-chodesh, yes, your fasting begins on the ninth, not because of
תוספת, that we already know. Because the eating done for the sake
of fasting makes it as if you fasted. So for some people,
this is a very important principle conceptually about what fasting is about.
One of the things we discussed at the beginning of the פרק
perek is, is fasting about hurting yourself, afflicting yourself, that some part
of the process of תשובה teshuva that, you know, you're beating yourself
up to some degree, you're making yourself miserable, or like the גמרא
said before of תשבתו שבתכם tishbesu shabbaskhem and the רמב"ם says no,
it's not about the pain and the suffering, it's about freeing yourself
from the physical world. So that idea that it's is supported by
this דרשה because what does it mean if you eat, it's like
you afflicted yourself additionally? You should say the opposite. You should say
if I'm eating a lot the day before, it makes it easier
for me to fast. That should undermine the fast. So some people
want to read it that way and say no, no, no, because
if, you know, if you really stuff yourself the day before, it
makes the fasting harder, you know, because psychologically. But the better explanation
is no, it's not about making it hard to fast, it's about
freeing yourself from the physical world. So actually, you do better by
eating appropriately the day before so you're not on יום כפור Yom
Kippur saying, oh my God, I can't wait till this day is
over until I can eat and so on, right? It's supposed to
be freeing yourself and and not removing your focus on the fasting
so you can free yourself for more spiritual matters. So it actually
makes the fast better if you eat
before, and that's why it's כאילו התענה, ke-illu his'anna, because it's not
about how you're hurting yourself, it's about what the state that you
are achieving. Okay. To be continued.